Finding Aid for Joseph K. Sano papers, 1923-1951
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joseph K. Sano papers 1923-1951 1941-1951
Sano, Joseph K.
1.4 linear feet
2013011 Aa 2
Joseph K. Sano was a Japanese living in the United States during World War II. He taught at the University of Michigan in the Military Intelligence Japanese Language School during the war and went on to assist in the war efforts by helping with bombing surveys and working as a translator in Japan during the trials for war crimes. Material is organized chronologically and ranges from 1923 to 1951. Papers mainly consist of correspondence and information pertaining to the various places of employment where Sano worked or served.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection was donated by Alice Sano Teachout (Donor 10806 ) in July 2012.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Joseph Kumao Sano was born on Awaji Island, Japan on March 4, 1890. He came to the United States in 1906 and served in the United States air service during World War I, after which he was granted naturalization as a United States citizen by a special act of Congress in 1919. Sano returned to Japan in 1924 where he married Sakae Ikuta. They returned to Los Angeles where they had three children: two sons, George and Roy, and a daughter, Alice. Sano graduated from the University of Southern California with a law degree in 1926 and continued his post-graduate work at Balboa Law College from 1938 to 1940. He opened his law office in Little Tokyo Los Angeles, the business center for the Japanese community of Los Angeles. Simultaneously he established two branches of the California Bank, principally for the Japanese community -- one on Terminal Island and one in the center of Little Tokyo.
In 1942, by executive order, Sano and his family were forced to move to the Santa Anita (racetrack) Assembly Center in Arcadia, California, a temporary holding center for citizens of Japanese ancestry. In November of 1942, Santa Anita was closed and Sano and his family were relocated to Jerome, Arkansas and remained there until 1943 when Sano moved to Ann Arbor, Michigan. Sano had been contracted to work as a Japanese language teacher at the Army's Military Intelligence School hosted at the University of Michigan. The Army course was designed to train American soldiers in Japanese language, culture, and geography. In 1945 he was instructed to participate in the Strategic Bombing Survey where he studied the effects of the atomic and hydrogen bombing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki. In December of 1945 he was sent to Tokyo for the International Military Tribunal of the Far East where he served as one of three language and court arbitrators, Sano being the bilingual arbitrator.
In 1948 he began working as a property control officer for the Bank of Japan. He was in charge of monitoring the transportation of gems and precious metals, such as gold, that were confiscated during the war from the Japanese people and were to be melted down for Japan's war effort. He continued to work there until 1951.
The collection mostly consists of correspondence and reports related to the various jobs and military postings that Joseph Sano had, beginning with his job at the California Bank, followed by his work at the University of Michigan, his position with the strategic bombing survey, his role in the war crime trials, and ending with his job as a property control officer.
The collection consists of two series: Joseph K. Sano Papers and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Sano, Joseph K.; Japanese Americans--Evaluation and relocation, 1942-1945.; Tokyo Trial, Tokyo, Japan, 1946-1948.; War crime trials--Japan.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Army Intensive Japanese Language School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Faculty.
Scrapbooks.; genre
- Joseph K. Sano Papers
  The Joseph K. Sano Papers contain files regarding Sano's employment and military service. The California Bank file from 1923 contains information about Sano when he worked for the bank, as well as his business card. The Relocation Program file from 1941 to 1942 includes copies of newspaper articles about the evacuation of Japanese during the war, a booklet about the Santa Anita internment camp, and identification cards belonging to Sano. The Military Intelligence School file from 1943 to 1945 mainly consists of correspondence to and from Sano regarding his employment with the University of Michigan. Also included are a photo of the teachers of the school, graduation dance programs for the class of 1945, and a program from Nips in the Bud performed at the University of Michigan in 1943 and signed by the cast. The Strategic Bombing Survey file from 1945 contains correspondence and forms sent to Sano while he was working on the survey project, as well as identification cards. The War Crime Trial Referee folder from 1945 to 1948 contains identification cards, correspondence, and information about the trial procedures. Also included is a book titled Album of International Military Tribunal for the Far East which contains information and pictures about the trial with text written in both English and Japanese. The Property Control Officer file from 1947 to 1951 consists of Sano's employment applications, correspondence, an inventory of gold items held by the bank, and reports regarding the control and release of precious metals. Also included in the collection is a Miscellaneous file containing two identification cards. One card is from 1930 regarding Sano's status as an alumnus of Southern California University, and the other a business card for Mr. Sano indicating his working for the Saginaw and Manistee Lumber Company.
  - California Bank Japanese Branch, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Relocation Program, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Military Intelligence School, 1943- 1945 (Box 1)
  - Strategic Bombing Survey, 1945 (Box 1)
  - War Crime Trial Referee, 1945-1948 (Box 1)
  - Property Control Officer, 1947-1951, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series contains two scrapbooks. The first scrapbook ranges from 1923 to 1929 and 1941 to 1943. Included are newspaper clippings of ads and announcements from the Japanese branch of the California Bank. Most of the text is in Japanese. Also included are papers relating to the relocation of Sano and his family. The second scrapbook contains newspaper clippings and photographs from the war crime trials, one of which was used in the January 26, 1948 issue of Life magazine. Also included are newspaper clippings discussing the evacuation of Japanese people, certificates awarded to Sano by the University of Michigan, photos of gold bars from the time he worked as a property control officer, and personal photos of Sano and his family in Japan and at his sister's funeral.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1923-1929, 1941-1943 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1940s (Box 2)